<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Sports &#8211; Tyc Ndcs Undp</title>
	<atom:link href="https://tyc.ndcs.undp.org/category/sports/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://tyc.ndcs.undp.org</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2023 18:33:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Cummins leads from front as Australia tighten grip on third Ashes Test</title>
		<link>https://tyc.ndcs.undp.org/cummins-leads-from-front-as-australia-tighten-grip-on-third-ashes-test/</link>
					<comments>https://tyc.ndcs.undp.org/cummins-leads-from-front-as-australia-tighten-grip-on-third-ashes-test/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[paglaadmin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2023 18:33:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Sports]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://tyc.ndcs.undp.org/?p=12</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Australia captain Pat Cummins sparked an England collapse to leave the tourists in command of the third Ashes Test and heading towards a series victory at Headingley on Friday. England were 142-7 at lunch on the second day, still 121 runs behind Australia&#8217;s first-innings 263. In a match they had to win at 2-0 down]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Australia captain Pat Cummins sparked an England collapse to leave the tourists in command of the third Ashes Test and heading towards a series victory at Headingley on Friday.</p>
<p>England were 142-7 at lunch on the second day, still 121 runs behind Australia&#8217;s first-innings 263.</p>
<p>In a match they had to win at 2-0 down with three to play, England lost four wickets for 74 runs in the session after resuming on 68-3, with fast bowler Cummins taking 4-59 in 13 overs.</p>
<p>But England captain Ben Stokes, fresh from his stunning 155 in Australia&#8217;s 43-run win in the second Test at Lord&#8217;s last week, was still there on 27 not out.England fans were left hoping the all-rounder could reproduce his Headingley Ashes heroics of 2019, when Stokes&#8217;s astounding unbeaten hundred guided England to a remarkable one-wicket win.</p>
<p>The hosts started the day with Joe Root 19 not out and Jonny Bairstow, whose controversial stumping exit at Lord&#8217;s provoked a furious row that drew comments from both the British and Australian prime ministers, unbeaten on one.</p>
<p>The pair received a rousing reception as they walked out to bat on a sunny morning at their Yorkshire home ground.</p>
<p>But Root fell for his overnight score with just the second ball of the day, when the star batsman tentatively edged Cummins to David Warner at first slip.</p>
<p>Bairstow then exited for 12 when he flat-footedly drove at a ball angled across him from left-arm fast bowler Mitchell Starc, with Steve Smith holding a sharp catch in front of his face at second slip.</p>
<p>The latest example of Australia&#8217;s superior fielding left England in dire straits at 87-5.</p>
<p>Stokes had made just 10 when given not out to paceman Scott Boland following an appeal for lbw that remained rejected despite a tight Australia review.</p>
<p>Moeen Ali, having got away with one miscued hook, then attempted a similar shot off Cummins and holed out for 21 as England slumped to 131-6.</p>
<p>And off what became the last ball before lunch, Chris Woakes also fell to the short-ball trap when caught behind for 10 trying to pull Starc.</p>
<p>World Test champions Australia, bidding for their first Ashes series win in England in 22 years, had been indebted Thursday to Mitchell Marsh.</p>
<p>The all-rounder marked his first Test since 2019 with a run-a-ball 118 in an innings where the next highest score was Travis Head&#8217;s 39.</p>
<p>Marsh, however, was dropped on 12 when Root floored a regulation slip catch.</p>
<p>Mark Wood took an impressive 5-34 in his first match of the series, with the fast bowler managing an average speed of over 90 mph.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://tyc.ndcs.undp.org/cummins-leads-from-front-as-australia-tighten-grip-on-third-ashes-test/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
